My lord, good morning.
大阁领早啊
It's quite late.
卯时已过
It seems the Ministry of Justice
看来平日里
isn't very strict with its staff.
刑部管教得并不严
Thanks to you,
托您的福
I slept really well last night.
昨晚我睡得可太好了
How credible are you in your judgment
你对凶手不是梁家二房
that the murderer isn't from the Liang family?
有几成把握
Ninety percent.
九成
Go investigate now,
快去查吧
while your head
趁现在你的脑袋
is still attached to your neck.
还在项颈之上
If you keep making me
再这样让我
stay up all night,
成宿地不睡觉
even if I can keep my head,
脑袋就算在
I probably won't live long anyway.
我也得去见阎王
My lord.
郎君
My lord, my lady,
郎君 夫人
breakfast is served.
用早食了
I have no appetite.
没胃口
Heavens.
嚯
What a mess.
真够乱的
Yan Xing.
颜幸
Xing.
六娘
Chuichui.
垂垂
Seriously?
你不是吧
They don't even feed you there?
沈府都不管饭的呀
Dining together with him?
跟他一起吃饭
Still alive.
还活着呢
I'd rather not.
我怕噎得慌
Looks like she's fine.
看着没什么事
Let's go.
走走走
You'd rather not?
噎得慌
Really?
不是吧
I've heard that you and the White Death
我听说你跟白无常
were very much in love.
可是伉俪情深
That you got along very well,
夫唱妇随
and supported each other.
比翼双飞
You even rode a horse together.
恩爱骑马的事
I've heard all about it.
我都听了
Come on, be honest.
老实交代
It's true about what the saying says,
果然
good news doesn't travel far,
好事不出门
but bad news spreads everywhere.
坏事传千里
Bad news?
坏事
You are now famous
你现在可在
among the noblewomen
皇城贵女圈里面
in the imperial city.
那是出了名的
Once,
当年
a woman pretended to faint
就是有个女子装晕
and fell into Shen Du's arms.
倒在了沈渡怀里
She was arrested by the Imperial Guard
就被内卫府抓进去了
and charged with
还判了一个
offending Chief Shen.
冒犯大阁领的罪
That is very him.
果真是他的风格
From then on,
自那以后啊
all the women
襄安城的女子
would avoid the White Death
见到白无常
like the plague.
避如蛇蝎
But he displayed affection and
他竟还跟你当街恩爱
was intimate with you on the street!
还亲密接触
I prefer to be less intimate.
还是少接触的好
This is...
这是
On your wedding night,
你大婚当晚
there was a fire at Ming Hall.
明堂大火
Her Highness was furious.
太皇太后震怒
Several people from the IG
内卫府好几个人
have been held accountable,
都被问责
and even Shen Du's salary
就连你夫君
has been cut.
也被罚了俸禄
Really?
还有这事
I heard that
我听说
poor scholar Chen Baiyi
那个叫陈白衣的穷书生
committed self-immolation
他是因为
in the Ming Hall because
求取功名而不得
he failed his exam.
才跑到明堂自焚的
Although he's dead,
这人已死
his family was supposed to be punished.
本来应该连坐
But
结果
the only one left in his family is this
他们家就只剩下
nearly sixty-year-old, frail elder
这个近六旬
who's almost deaf and blind.
眼花耳聋的老人
Her Highness, in her benevolence,
太皇太后仁慈
has granted her pardon.
本来给她赦免了
But this old lady
结果这老太太
has been sitting here
竟然跑到刑部门口
in front of the Ministry of Justice
来久坐
day and night,
说是非要伸冤
demanding justice.
一坐就是一天一夜
Think about it,
你想想
who dares to take on
这烫手山芋
such a risky case.
这谁敢接啊
Do you have a death wish?
你不要脑袋了
They will kill me either way.
怎么着都要掉脑袋
I only have one life, what else can they do?
反正我只有一个头
Madam,
老人家
please get up.
有什么事您先起来
If there is indeed any injustice,
若真有冤屈
we will surely find out
我们一定会
what really happened.
给您一个说法的
Thank you, Lady.
谢谢你 姑娘
Who was that bold
是谁那么大胆子
and took that old lady's case?
收了那老太太的状
C'mon,
来来来
come forward yourself.
自己站出来啊
I'm in a good mood today.
我今天心情好
I promise to spare your life.
保证不打死你
Who took her case?
这谁收她状子了
That Lady Chen outside?
门口那个陈老太吗
I already took her home.
我已经把人家送回家了
You are all dismissed.
散了散了
Let's go, let's go.
走走走 散了散了
How it is y...
怎么又是
Actually, we should have
其实老太太呢
comforted the old lady.
是应该好好安抚一下
Otherwise, she would just
要不然成天蹲在
keep sitting in front of the
我刑部大门口
office everyday.
算怎么回事
About the case of Chen Baiyi's
关于陈白衣自焚
self-immolation,
这个案子
I have already...
我已经很认真地
The follow-up will now be handled by...
此事的后续呢就交给
Feng Gui!
冯贵
You just keep an eye on the old lady
你帮我盯着老太太
and don't let her come again.
别让她再来了啊
I'd rather not.
我就别了
Chief Clerk Wu,
吴主事
I think...
我觉得
Everyone, gather around.
都过来 都过来
The IG has taken over the murder case
梁府梁尘重的命案
of Liang Chenzhong from the Liang family.
内卫府接手了
No one
所有人
is to intervene again.
不许再插手
The IG
内卫府啊
is not a place where
不是可以
we should intervene.
随便插手的地方
Anyone who disobeys
如有不从
will face severe punishment from me.
本官严惩不贷
Yes.
是
Get back to your work.
忙去吧 忙去吧
Chief Clerk Wu, I...
吴主事 我
Yan Xing,
颜幸
Chuichui,
垂垂
don't you two still have some files
你们俩不是还有卷宗
to organize?
没有整理好吗
Keep going.
努力
I'm really...
我真是
Xing,
六娘
I just remembered that
我突然想起来
weren't you going to have lunch
沈大阁领不是要
together with Chief Shen?
约你午食吗
It's getting late.
时候也不早了呢
There's really no rush
这个
with the files.
卷宗也没那么着急
Lunch is more important.
午食要紧
Let's go.
走
You should give up your small business.
把你那小买卖放下吧
and follow me.
跟着我
Okay.
行
Thank you.
那就仰仗您了
Madam, I'm sorry.
官娘子多有得罪
Tongming Pavilion has a rule of
通明馆向来规定
only admitting male guests
只接男宾
and does not accept females guests.
不进女宾
We're not guests.
我们不是宾客
We're here for official matters.
官家办案
Then how about
那不如
you send a male official instead?
另派男官来办可好
Although I am just a clerk,
我虽是书吏
but she
可这位
is a distinguished ninth-rank clerk
是刑部在录的
on record with the Ministry of Justice.
堂堂九品书令史
Your obstruction
你们如此阻拦
seems to question
莫不是
the official selection process
对官家选拔官吏的制度
for officials.
有异
Madam, please don't make things difficult.
官娘子不要为难小人
If I let you two ladies in
今日要是让两位娘子
today,
入了这门
I'm afraid,
恐怕
I won't be able to
小的这饭碗
keep my job.
也就保不住了
Then how about you
那不如
take a closer look?
你再仔细看看
Are we female guests
我们是男宾
or male guests?
还是女宾啊
Male guests.
男宾
This way, please.
两位请
My poor Zhanxin,
我的盏心
how could she be so unfortunate?
怎么会如此命苦
When she met Liang Chenzhong,
原想着以为
I thought she could
她遇到梁尘重
marry into a good family.
能做个良籍妾室
Who is so ruthless
究竟是哪个丧心病狂的
and killed her?
杀害了她
Madam, our condolences.
坊主节哀
Do you still remember
你还记不记得
if there was anything
邝盏心失踪之前
out of the ordinary
可有发生过
before Kuang Zhanxin disappeared,
什么异常之事
or
或者说
if she had
她跟别人
any arguments with anyone?
有没有起过争执
Zhanxin has always been gentle
盏心性子素来温和
and got along well with her sisters
与各姐妹和近邻
and neighbors.
相处愉快
So before the officials informed you
昨夜官府来告知之前
last night, you didn't know
你还不知道
that Kuang Zhanxin was missing?
邝盏心失踪了
She left on the 17th of last month
她是于上月十七出的门
to go on a trip with Liang Chenzhong.
同梁尘重一同去郊游
Liang Chenzhong
往常梁尘重
has taken her on trips before.
也会带着她出去玩
So I thought this time
我以为这次
was just a longer trip.
只是去了久了点
If there's more questions,
日后若有需要
we'll come back in the future.
再来相问
Please accept my deepest condolences.
还请多节哀
I heard Chen Baiyi not only set himself
听说那个陈白衣自焚
on fire but also burned down the Ming Hall.
还火烧了明堂
Thankfully, you kicked him out early.
好在你一早撵他出门
In Dacang, it's all about connections.
大苍讲的是门荫取仕
A nobody from a poor family like him
他一寒门
dreaming of rising to greatness?
还想飞上枝头当凤凰
He was simply delusional.
简直是痴心妄想
He was lucky that
他能给我润笔
I let him write for me.
那是他的福分
But he's still not content.
他竟然还不知足
These poor scholars
这帮穷酸书生
are so ungrateful.
就是不知好歹
He was just a study companion,
一个陪读
yet he wanted to take the top spot in
还想抢
the Hongwen Hall's literary competition?
弘文馆文比试第一
How preposterous!
我呸
Here, drink!
来 喝
Here here.
来 来
Xing.
六娘
Let's go.
走
Xu Shuai.
徐帅
Clerk Lu.
陆书令史
you're here at Tongming Pavilion on a case?
你来通明馆是有案子
The very one
就是被你郎君
your husband took over.
截胡的那个案子
I probably shouldn't call you
想来不该再
Xing anymore,
叫你六娘才对
I should address you as Lady.
应该唤作大阁领夫人
Xu Shuai,
徐帅
just call me Xing
你还是同往常一样
as usual.
喊我六娘吧
Okay.
行
Then stop calling me
那你以后
Xu Shuai as well.
也别叫我徐帅了
You can just call me Shuai.
叫我徐大哥吧
Okay,
好
Shuai.
徐大哥
After the death of Kuang Zhanxin
那邝盏心的事
blazed about,
传出去之后
every family near the
这平康坊附近的
Pingkang music house
各家坊主
is on the edge.
就跟中了邪一样
If a daughter
总觉得
has been out for too long,
自己家出去久了
they would think that
没回来的姑娘
she's gone missing.
就是失踪
We already have more than a dozen reports.
这都报了十几起案子了
Someone else went missing?
还有人失踪
No.
没有
There were 17 girls reported missing.
十七个姑娘刚报失踪
We already found 15 of them.
已经找回来十五个了
And the other two
还剩两个呢
should be fine as well.
大致也没什么问题
But there's another thing.
但是有一件事情
I was just deciding if
本还没有想好
I should report it,
要不要上报
before I ran into you here.
就在这儿遇到了你们
This document records the missing cases
这上面记录着
of songstresses over the years.
这些年的歌伎失踪案
That's odd.
奇怪
Although these songstresses
这些歌伎
aren't the top performers
虽然不都是
in their houses,
各坊的当红头牌
they were all well-versed in music,
但都通晓音律
excelled in instrumental skills,
以器乐为长
and were especially skilled in pipa.
精通琵琶
That's right.
没错
It was too much of a coincidence.
就是太过巧合
That's why I find it odd.
所以才觉得蹊跷
These are their portraits.
这些是失踪女子的画像
All these women
这些女子
had the same hairstyle.
都梳着相同的飞仙髻
Did you notice anything else?
可还有发现
Look,
你们看
despite the differences
这些女子的面容
in their facial features,
虽然都不相同
they shared certain common elements,
却又都有共通之处
especially in their expressions,
尤其是神态
which were remarkably alike.
极为相似
Yeah.
对
There is an inexplicable similarity
这乍一看
at first glance.
有种说不出来的相似
I intended to turn these
这些卷宗
files over to the Ministry of Justice,
我本来想交给你们刑部
but then I feared it might
但又觉得
be inappropriate to bypass the IG.
不便绕过内卫府上报
Now it seems
现在看来
best for you to take them.
由你接收最好
The White Death
那白无常
isn't going to kill his wife for this,
总不会因此拔刀杀妻
right?
是吧
I'll excuse myself then.
那在下先告辞了
You left this morning with confident attitude,
一早上信誓旦旦
betting against me.
打赌出门
I thought you were investigating,
还以为在查什么
turns out you were just chitchatting.
原来在此闲聊
I was discussing the case
我可是在和
with Xu Shuai, who is in charge of
统领全城异良人的徐帅
the Delinquent.
探讨案情
In charge?
统领全城
Really?
这么厉害
Xu Shuai was once
徐帅当年
a notorious outlaw with a reward of
可是被朝廷重金十万两
one hundred thousand taels on his head.
悬赏通缉的大侠盗
So Xu Shuai
原来徐帅
was the legendary thief who
就是传说中
broke into the palace and
潜入宫中
stole the Queen Mother's jade pillow?
偷了太皇太后玉枕的那位
Sounds impressive,
说得厉害
but he was still captured, wasn't he?
还不是被逮了
Even so,
虽然被逮
but the Queen Mother valued his talent.
可是太皇太后惜才
She not only spared him
不但没有给他降罪
but also freed him from slavery.
还脱了他的奴籍
It doesn't matter.
被逮了就是被逮了
He was captured,
那就是略逊一筹
that means he was incompetent.
技不如人
I...
我
Can you really solve the case
和这样的人在一起
with someone like that?
能讨论出什么样的案情
Of course I can.
我能探讨出
I'm about to win
有关梁家的赌局
our bet on the Liang Case.
我就快赢了
All the evidence
如今的证据
points to
桩桩件件都指向
this being an ongoing
这是延续多年的
serial murder case.
连环杀人案
Once I find the real murderer,
待我找出真凶
the Liang family
梁家二房便能
will be fully cleared of suspicion.
彻底洗清嫌疑
Chief Shen,
大阁领
reports from our eyes said that
盯梁家的人回报
the main branch of the Liang family
说梁家二房
splashed chicken blood on the second branch,
被大房的人淋了鸡血
driving Second Madame further into madness.
梁二夫人变得更疯了
And Liang Chenyu went to the
梁三郎心一横
Ministry of Justice and turned himself in.
竟然去刑部自首了
Moreover,
还有
Prince Ying said she wanted to see you.
英王殿下那边说想见您
Prince Ying
英王殿下
only asked Chief Shen to go in.
只请大阁领一人入内
The imprisonment of Liang Chenyu is not
梁尘昱入狱
something Her Highness would wish.
此事并非太皇太后所愿
If I'm not wrong,
本宫要是没有记错的话
Her Highness
太皇太后
didn't ask Chief Shen
并未要求大阁领
to look into that case.
彻查此案
Rather, she asked you to protect the Liangs.
而是让你力保梁家二房
There isn't enough evidence
现在证据还不充足
for a verdict yet.
未有定论
You have always been meticulous,
大阁领做事向来严谨
but this time,
可这次
you've been reluctant to act by the book.
却迟迟不按规矩办事
Just don't be like your father,
可不要学你那父亲
keeping your plans all to yourself.
闷声做大事
I don't dare.
微臣不敢
Her Highness must be intentionally
英王殿下必是在
giving Chief Shen a hard time.
刁难大阁领
The Queen Mother
这梁府的案子
had made it clear that we should protect
太皇太后早就交代过
the second branch of the Liang family.
要保下梁家二房
But my lady,
可夫人你
you insisted on digging deeper.
却非要一查到底
Now, look what's happened,
这下好了
Liang Chenyu is in prison.
梁三郎被入了大狱
How is Chief Shen supposed to
这下怎么让大阁领
explain this to the higher-ups?
跟上面交代
I'll take full responsibility for the case
这个案子我会负责到底
and promise a satisfactory
一定会给上面
explanation for those above.
一个交代的
The Queen Mother trusts you,
太皇太后信任大阁领
I naturally trust you too.
本宫自然也是信任的
I only wish that
只是希望大阁领
you don't let my trust in you down.
不要辜负了这份信任
I heard that your newly wed wife,
听说刚过门的沈夫人
Lady Shen is quite interesting.
人也是有趣得紧啊
I'm very grateful to the Queen Mother
太皇太后赐婚
for granting me this marriage.
微臣感恩不尽
Chief Shen,
大阁领
five more pairs of bodies
西明寺那边
were just dug up near Ximing Temple,
挖出了五对尸首
the cause of death is the same as the others.
死状与之前的两具一样
So it seems
如此看来
this case indeed
此事的确
has nothing to do with the Liang family.
与梁家二房无关
Along with the two bodies previously found,
加上梁尘重之前那两具
we now have six pairs,
六对男女
making twelve bodies in total.
十二具尸体
The killer's method remained consistent.
凶手作案手法相同
The men had their hearts cut out,
男的被挖心
and the women were disfigured.
女的被毁容
This is not mud from Ximing Temple.
这不是西明寺的泥土
These bodies
这些尸体
have been moved
是最近被挪过的
and reburied recently.
重新被掩埋的
Her face is dark purple,
脸乌紫
with skin and flesh turned outward,
皮肉外翻
but you can still tell
但还是能看出
she was a young woman.
这是个妙龄女子
Can you determine
遇难时间
the time of death?
可以推测出来吗
These two people
这两人
were probably killed last month.
应该是在前月被杀害的
Around the bodies,
尸体的周围
there are layers of charcoal and wood ash,
有许多层木炭和草木灰
probably to hide the odor.
应该是用来掩盖气味的
But what is this peculiar fragrance?
这香味到底是什么呢
Anything out of the norm?
可有异常
If my master was here,
我师父要是在的话
he would surely be able to tell
一定能辨出
what else is in there.
这里面含有什么
From what I see,
依我看
you've already inherited
你已经继承了
your master's legacy.
你师父的衣钵
Maybe even better that
更不输民间
the legendary detective, Pan Chi.
第一神探潘驰
Not even close!
差得远着呢
After his retirement, my master has been
我师父他隐退之后
traveling the world
游历四方
and probably doesn't even remember that
怕是都快忘记
I was his apprentice.
我这个徒弟了
These are
这是挖到
the earliest two bodies we've found.
最早的一对尸体
The decomposition is the most severe.
腐化最为严重
It's very hard to pinpoint
被害时间
the exact time of death.
很难具体推测出
It should be
应该是在
between four to six years ago.
四到六年间
If it's the same murderer,
若凶手为同一人
he's truly ruthless,
那也太丧心病狂了
cutting open the chest, removing the heart.
剖膛挖心
It's probably
应该是个
a strong man,
孔武有力的男子
maybe a butcher.
说不定是个屠夫
I think,
依我所见
the suspect is most likely
凶手极为可能
a woman.
是女子
Why?
为何
The wounds on the female victims' faces,
这每具女尸脸上的伤痕
their placement,
位置
length,
长度
and depth
深浅
are almost exactly the same.
几乎别无二致
And the force used with the knife
而且这用刀的力度
doesn't seem to be that of a man.
也不像是男子所为
If the killer was a woman,
若凶手为女子
she killed 12 people
她要在这些年里
these years.
连杀十二人
These male victims
这些男性死者
were not old or weak.
也并非老弱病残
They were in their prime when they died.
死的时候也都是青壮年
How were they overpowered by a woman?
怎么可能不敌一个女子
Shuai,
徐大哥
if we think something is impossible
若是因为没有见过
simply because we haven't seen it before,
便觉得不可能
many strange cases in this world
那这世上许多奇案
would've never been solved.
都无法告破了
Let's go.
走
What...
你
What are you doing?
你到底要干什么
Prince Ying has already ordered that
英王殿下已经吩咐
the cases of Ximing Temple
西明寺的案子
and the Liang family
和梁府一案
be merged
并案处理
and handled solely by the IG.
统归内卫府管
The officials of the Ministry of Justice
刑部的人
can't no longer intervene.
都不能再插手
Fine.
不管便不管
I'll take you to a place first.
我先带你去个地方
Where?
去哪儿啊
You...
你
Her sleeves are filled
她两袖中
with the fragrance of white sandalwood.
是白脑香的味道
A silk garment with embroidered patterns,
丝制如意纹锦衣
a jade hairpin,
翡翠绒花钗
and a peony-patterned white silk fan.
牡丹白绢罗扇
Instead of dawdling here,
有时间在这儿发呆
why don't you try to figure out
不如好好想想
how to keep your head?
该怎么保住自己的脑袋
Where are we going exactly?
到底要去哪儿
The Ministry of Justice.
刑部
Let me off.
你快放我下来
We're near the Ministry of Justice.
前面离刑部不远了
I can walk there myself.
我自己可以走过去
The real killer is still on the loose.
真凶还未找到
Liang Chenyu is still in prison.
梁三郎还在狱中
If anything happens to him,
他若有事
you'll go keep him company in hell.
你去给他陪葬
Chief Shen,
沈大阁领
I have never lost
我颜六娘打的赌
a bet before.
从未输过
Chief Shen, what brings you here to
大阁领今日怎么有空
the Ministry of Justice today?
来我们刑部
I can't come here?
我不能来
Chief Shen, what are you saying?
大阁领这说哪里话
Of course you're welcome to come here.
欢迎 欢迎
I'm here to ask you for someone
来跟你要个人
to help out at the IG.
去内卫府帮忙
Chief Shen, you want to make a transfer?
大阁领要调人啊
That's easy.
此事容易
Who do you want to transfer,
大阁领要调谁
I'll go arrange it right away.
下官这就去安排
Her.
就她了
The Ximing Temple case has been
西明寺十尸案
fully handed over to the IG.
已全权交由内卫府处理
The Ministry of Justice should step back.
你们刑部就别管了
Yes.
是
Chief Shen,
大阁领
I still have many case files
我还有许多案宗
to record.
都没有录完
I can't be transferred to the IG now.
怕是不便调去内卫府
Clerk Yan, what are you talking about?
颜书吏说什么呢
Just give your case files
卷宗没整理完
to Clerk Lu.
交给陆书令史
Go ahead, go with Chief Shen.
你快去随大阁领去
If Clerk Yan doesn't come,
颜书吏不来
this case is closed.
此案就这么结了
Chief Clerk Wu,
吴主事
take those bodies outside the city,
把那堆尸骨拖去城外
find a place and bury them.
随便找个地方埋了
No.
不可
Fine, I'm coming.
我这就去
Xing.
六娘
These were found at Chen Baiyi's home.
陈白衣家翻出来的
There are some essays he wrote.
他写过的文章
I already read them.
我都看了
The writing was remarkable.
篇篇文采斐然
Thank you for your
这段日子
hard work these days.
真的苦了你了
It's nothing.
不苦
Just take me to the Furong Theater.
芙蓉园看戏
Okay!
准了
Be careful.
小心点
Chief Shen,
大阁领
the preliminary forensic report is ready.
仵作已经初步完成化验
Jinglin, should any officials
景林
from the Ministry of Justice be
日后若发现
found investigating this case privately,
刑部的人私查此案
charge them with collusion.
全部按结党营私处理
Yes.
是
Then I'll have to thank you
那我还得多谢
for transferring me,
大阁领的提携之恩了
allowing me
让我还有
to continue working on this case.
查这案子的权利
I will give it my all
日后我定当竭尽全力
and solve it as soon as possible.
早日破案
That's good.
夫人知道就好
Now that I'm here,
既然借入了内卫府
I am
那下官
a part of the IG.
就是内卫府的一员
I'll have to follow the rules
自然要遵守
of the IG.
内卫府的规矩
I'm only a clerk,
小的不过是书吏
how can I ride a horse
怎么能与大阁领
together with the Chief?
同骑一匹马呢
I am not skilled in horseback riding,
下官马术不精
but I trust that Jinglin
景内卫体恤下属
will surely not
必定是不会
just leave me behind,
丢下下官不管的
right?
对不对
Me?
我
Then Jinglin,
那今日就还要
today you'll have to make do
委屈一下景内卫
and ride together with me.
和下官同骑一乘了
My lady, if you wish to ride a horse,
夫人若是想骑马
you should do so with the Chief.
自然是同大阁领一起
I'll...
小的那
I'll lead your horse.
小的给您牵马
How can that be?
那多不好意思
Let's ride together.
还是一起骑吧
In work, gender does not matter.
办案无男女
Jinglin,
景内卫
just think of me
就把我当成
as a regular colleague.
寻常同僚便是
My lady, I'll just lead the horse.
夫人还是坐好吧
How much longer are you going to chitchat?
还要闲聊到什么时候
If you continue this,
再这么散漫闲谈
you'll be fined half a year's salary.
罚你半年的俸禄
I... I...
我 我
Chief Shen.
大阁领
These
这些
are taken from
是从最早遇害的
the earliest pair of victims.
那对尸身上取下的
Made in
监工于
the first year of the Shengli era.
圣历元年
This was on the
这是最早遇害的
earliest male victim.
那名男尸所佩戴的
The first crime
凶手初次作案
most likely took place six years ago.
应该是在六年前
Why's that?
为何
The method of killing
凶手每次杀人手法
has remained consistent.
如出一辙
The timing of the crime
作案时间
likely follows a pattern as well.
想必也有其规律
Even a small mistake
所谓差之毫厘
can lead to a major mistake.
失之千里
If we get it wrong,
若是推测错了
it would make it even harder
想要找出真凶
to find the killer.
就没那么容易了
The Treasure Double Fish Pattern.
宝相双鱼纹
Jinxiu Silk Workshop.
锦绣坊
The Treasure Double Fish Pattern
这宝相双鱼纹
was a signature design created by
是锦绣坊当年
the renowned Jinxiu Silk Workshop.
特制的花样
It was a nationwide sensation.
风靡全国
Jinxiu Silk Workshop was the premier
锦绣坊是当年皇城
silk provider to the palace,
第一大丝绸坊
delivering on the first day of each month.
每月初一进贡绸缎进宫
However, in June of the third year of the Shengli era,
只是圣历三年六月
the workshop was charged with defiance
锦绣坊因献给
for making excessive garments
汝宁长公主夏衣逾制
for Princess Runing.
获了忤逆之罪
That's why since then,
所以自那之后
no one in the imperial city
皇城里再也没人
dared to wear their fabrics anymore.
敢穿锦绣坊的料子出门
Therefore, this man
这男尸
must have been killed
必是死于
before the Jinxiu Silk incident.
锦绣坊忤逆案之前
The gold plaque was made the first year
金牌制于圣历元年
of the Shengli era, so it's possible that
那人死于圣历元年
he was killed that year.
也不是没可能啊
Impossible.
不可能
The Treasure Double Fish Pattern
宝相双鱼纹
was a spring garment design by Jinxiu workshop
是圣历三年
in the third year of the Shengli era.
锦绣坊所制春衣样式
Sold only from February to April that year.
只在当年二至四月有售
You remember it this clearly?
记得这么清楚
There's a dossier
案卷处有
from the Jinxiu Workshop at the Archive,
锦绣坊旧案的卷宗
with a volume of
有一卷绘物册
illustrated patterns
上面载录了
covering ten years.
锦绣坊十年的花纹样式
Jinglin,
景林
go compare them.
去比对确认
Make sure it's right.
不可出错
Yes.
是
My lady,
夫人
the Archive is filled with
案卷处内
valuable items and rare books.
都是珍品和藏书典籍
Please do not wander around.
切勿乱走
Or touch anything unnecessarily.
也切勿乱动
I got it, I got it.
知道了知道了
We'll be faster if we split up.
我们分头找更快
You go over there.
你去那边
Please be careful.
切勿乱动啊
Compilation of Essays from Hongwen Hall.
弘文馆选试文章合录
Be quick!
手头都麻利点啊
Quickly, quickly.
快点快点快点
Don't drop it.
别掉地下了给
How are you so careless?
怎么回事都
Wait, wait, wait.
等会儿等会儿等会儿
Hey,
不是
why are you here?
你怎么来了
Weren't you transferred
你不是调去
to the IG?
内卫府去了吗
I need to see Chief Clerk Wu.
我要见吴主事
There's been progress in the Chen Baiyi case.
陈白衣自焚案有了进展
The Chief Clerk has instructed that
主事叮嘱过了
no one is to bring up the
明堂焚烧案
Chen Baiyi case again.
一律人等不能再提
Whoever does
如若再问
will lose their jobs.
递交辞呈来
There is indeed something behind it.
真的有内情
I need to see Chief Clerk Wu.
我要见吴主事
Wait a moment.
你等会儿等会儿
Didn't you see that?
你没看见吗
The whole Ministry of Justice
今天整个刑部
has been running around all day
被一首童谣弄得是
because of a children's rhyme.
焦头烂额的
Who has the time to
谁还有时间
look into the self-immolation case,
跟你查什么自焚案啊
you see?
是不是
What children's rhyme?
什么童谣
You didn't know?
你不知道啊
This could get you killed.
要掉脑袋呀
It's spread to
皇城里家家户户
everyone in the city.
都传遍了
Who knows who will be held accountable
真的不知道这次
this time.
是哪里又要遭殃了
Slow down, slow down.
你慢点慢点慢点
Watch the stairs.
小心台阶
People are heartless,
人无心
Buddha eats hearts,
佛食心
chaos rises beneath the Emperor's feet,
天子脚下乱纲章
Buddha eats hearts to hide sins.
佛陀食心把罪藏
The Dark Demon is here!
黑罗刹来了
Kid,
小朋友
did you know what you just said
你可知你刚才的话
was an act of treachery?
实属大逆不道
How do you think
你说
you should be punished?
该怎么惩罚你呢
Do you want to try this new invention,
试试这新发明的
'I invite you into the jar'.
请君入瓮
Later,
待会儿
we'll put the jar on the fire,
把瓮放到火上一烤
you'll have more fun.
你会玩得更开心的
Guards.
来人
No, My Lord, no!
不要 大人  不要
No, My Lord!
不要 大人
My Lord, please!
大人 不要
My Lord, he's just a child.
大人 他还只是个孩子
Please let him go, My Lord.
求您放过他吧 大人
If such treacherous rumors
随意谣传这种
are spread freely,
大逆不道的话
won't the imperial city
那皇城
become
岂不是要成
a lawless place?
无人管辖之地了
No, My Lord, please.
不 大人 冤枉
If you won't discipline your kid,
你们不好好教育孩童
then I'll do it for you.
我便替你们教育
Mercy, My Lord.
不要啊 大人
Make way for the royal carriage.
英王车辇 让道
Prince Ying.
英王殿下
She looks familiar.
此人有点眼熟
What's going on? What's with the noise?
何事如此喧扰
Your Majesty,
殿下
please save my child!
求求你救救我的孩子
I came to patrol the streets today and
下官今日特来街上巡视
overheard a child's treacherous remarks.
忽听一孩童口出狂言
What he said was outrageous.
大逆不道
That's why I apprehended him.
这才将孩童拿下
I apologize for disturbing Your Majesty.
惊扰了殿下
I see.
原来如此
Your Majesty, please show mercy.
殿下开恩啊
My child's words were unfiltered.
小孩口无遮拦
I will make sure
草民定会带回去
he is properly disciplined.
好好教养
Yes, Your Majesty.
是啊 殿下
It is the parents' responsibility
子不教
if a child is not taught properly.
父之过
You're also at fault.
你们也难辞其咎
Chancellor Lai,
来中丞
everyone makes mistakes.
人非圣贤 孰能无过
Moreover,
更何况
this is just a young child.
这只是一个黄口小儿
Chancellor, you're known for your wisdom.
来中丞向来英明
Surely, it is not worth tarnish
又何必为了一个孩子
your reputation for a child.
有损自己的英名呢
That being said.
话虽如此
Since I met this child today,
今日本宫既然见到了
it must
就说明
be a sign of destiny.
这孩子跟本宫有缘
Chancellor Lai,
来中丞
could you spare this child
可否看在本宫的面子上
for my sake?
饶了这个孩子
Since Your Majesty has spoken,
英王殿下开口
of course I'll let him go.
下官自然是要放人的
Let him go.
放人
Thank you, Your Majesty.
谢谢殿下 谢大人
As long as the child is fine.
孩子没事就好
Thank you, My lord.
谢谢大人
Go now.
去吧
-Thank you, Your Majesty. -Thank you, Your Majesty.
谢谢殿下 谢谢殿下
Her Majesty
英王殿下
is truly kind!
果真是菩萨心肠
Her Majesty is truly forgiving
英王殿下真是宽宏大量
and merciful.
慈悲为怀
Farewell, Your Majesty.
恭送殿下
Twenty strokes of punishment for you.
回去领二十杖
Yes.
是
Who is that woman?
那个女人究竟是谁
What's going on?
怎么了
Lai Luozhi reported to the court
来罗织御前告状
that Chief has failed the investigation.
说大阁领查案不力
Her Highness has issued a decree
太皇太后就下旨
to take Chief Shen away.
把大阁领带走了
You two, keep watch at the entrance.
你们俩门口守着
If there's any news about Chief Shen,
大阁领有任何消息
report immediately.
及时禀报
Yes.
是
You can't go in.
不得入内
Chief Shen has instructed that
大阁领吩咐
no one is allowed to
未经允许
approach the office without permission.
任何人不得靠近办公署
Anyone who disobeys...
违者
You want to go in by force?
想闯
Then
想闯你就
you'll have to step over me.
从我身上踩过去
Don't look around.
不许翻
Don't force me to take actions.
再翻我可对你不客气
Stop looking around,
你别再翻了
or I'll kill myself.
再翻我就自尽
If you want Chief Shen
如果你嫌
to die,
你家大阁领命长的话
then go ahead.
就动手吧
Grind the ink.
研墨
Hopefully, there's still time to
希望还能赶得及
submit the booklet.
呈上折子
The handwriting is identical
竟然跟大阁领
to Chief Shen's.
一样的字迹
Are you sure
你有把握
you can save Chief Shen
这样真的可以
this way?
救大阁领吗
Maybe he won't come out unscathed,
不能说一定能全身而退
but I have to at least try.
但好歹要试一试
Maybe he can avoid severe punishment.
兴许能免了重责
What are you waiting for?
还愣着干吗
Go now.
快去啊
I'll wait here.
我在府里等着
Don't look around.
你别再乱翻了
Your Majesty,
太皇太后
the IG has taken over the case for days
内卫府接手多日
yet it remains unsolved.
却迟迟未能破案
Now rumors are spreading that
如今坊间流言四起
the court's officials are ineffectual,
说朝廷用人不力
and some even speculate that the Emperor
更有甚者揣测帝心
is intentionally favoring the Liangs and
是在有意袒护梁家
it can damage Your Majesty's reputation.
实属有损太皇太后英名
I respectfully urge Your Majesty to
臣恳请太皇太后
transfer the case to Imperial Inspectorate.
让御察司接手此事
What you have said
来爱卿所言
is exactly what worries me.
也正是哀家忧心的事
Shen Du from the IG.
内卫府沈渡带到
Shen Du, of the IG,
内卫府大阁领沈渡
greets Your Majesty.
见过太皇太后
Long live Your Majesty.
太皇太后千岁千千岁
Shen Du,
沈爱卿啊
the case of the Liang family
梁家的案子
remains yet unsolved,
迟迟未破
do you have an explanation
你是否应该
for me?
给哀家一个交代了
Your Majesty,
禀太皇太后
the Liang murder is not an isolated case
梁家命案并非单独个案
but is connected with several bodies
而是与接连在西明寺
found recently at Ximing Temple,
挖掘出的多具尸体有关
all linked to the same murderer.
且为同一凶手犯案
The IG has been working diligently to
内卫府已根据证据
merge the cases based on the evidence.
加紧并案处理
This case involves several
梁府一案牵扯朝堂重臣
high-ranking court officials,
西明寺更是
and Ximing Temple is a place of Buddhism.
清修礼佛之地
Remaining unresolved, it has led to the
如今悬案难平
spread of a children's rhyme in the city,
城中已风靡起一阕童谣
with offensive content.
内容不堪入耳
Tell me what it says.
说来听听
If I may be so bold,
那臣就斗胆
I will recite this rhyme to
将这首童谣
Your Majesty.
说与太皇太后听
"People are heartless,"
人无心
"Buddha eats hearts,"
佛食心
"chaos rises beneath the Emperor's feet,"
天子脚下乱纲章
"Buddha eats hearts to hide sins."
佛陀食心把罪藏
This is outrageous!
放肆
Your Majesty, do not be angered.
太皇太后息怒
I think,
臣觉得
the reason this rhyme has spread
这童谣之所以传开
is due to the unresolved nature of the
都是因西明寺命案
Ximing Temple murder case.
悬而不定
If the IG still can't find the culprit,
内卫府再找不出真凶
they might as well
那还不如干脆
hold a ritual to
办一场驱邪的法会
drive away evil spirits.
管用些
Your Majesty,
太皇太后凤颜天下
you don't need to pay attention
自不必理会
to these superstitious rumors.
这些妄谈神鬼的言论
Chief Shen,
沈大阁领
did you forget this?
可是落了这个
The guards came abruptly to take me,
千牛卫突然上门拿人
when I was just sorting through some details,
微臣正在梳理案情
intending to present them to Your Majesty.
想要呈于太皇太后
"Only with the Buddha's heart can the world remain peaceful,
好一句太平人间唯佛心
and wicked thoughts be gone forever.
万劫歹念终不复
Uncover the truth and clear the grievances,
抽丝剥茧洗冤情
seeing clearly brings peace to the realm."
明察秋毫天下安啊
Okay.
好啊
Since you have
那既然
discovered various clues
已经查到了
connecting the Liang family
梁家和西明寺的
and Ximing Temple,
诸多线索
just move faster with the investigation.
那就推进吧
I accept your order.
臣领命
Lord Shen,
沈爱卿
you also mentioned in the booklet that
你在折子里还提到
the self-immolation has hidden motives.
明堂自焚另有内情
The person
自焚者
did not do it to vent frustration
不是为了要宣泄不满
but rather to express their resolve to me
而是以死向哀家言志
with their death.
无奈之举
Is that true?
属实吗
I'm looking into it.
臣正在复核
I'll report soon.
会尽快呈报
Your Majesty.
太皇太后
Okay, enough.
好了好了
Both of you
你们两位啊
are my trusted aides,
都是哀家的左膀右臂
each with your own strengths.
各有千秋
Okay then.
行了
That's it for today.
今日就到这儿吧
Go back now.
都回去吧
Shen Du,
沈爱卿
please wait.
你留步
There is another matter
哀家还有一件事
I need you to attend to right away.
要让你即刻去办
I accept your order.
臣领旨
Chief Shen.
沈大阁领
You were calm and eloquent
今日在太皇太后面前
in front of Her Highness
沈大阁领面不改色
today.
巧舌如簧
It was truly impressive.
真是让人佩服
Your praise is too kind, Chancellor Lai.
来中丞谬赞了
I was merely telling the truth.
在下不过是陈述事实
People say that
人们都说
the IG
内卫府
is like Her Highness's eyes.
是太皇太后的一双眼
It's better if the eyes
可眼睛成天乱转
don't look into the wrong direction.
别盯错了方向才好
The IG is just doing their job
内卫府的所作所为
within their jurisdiction,
都在分内之中
unlike the Imperial Inspectorate,
不像御察司
targeting everyone in sight.
一口獠牙四处撕咬
If it were someone else,
若是换作了旁人
they might find themselves overwhelmed.
恐怕还真分身乏术
Then I sincerely wish you
那就希望
can solve the case soon.
沈大阁领早日破案
There are many who
可是有很多人
are waiting to make their move.
在磨牙呢